<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached on the thirtieth of January, 1678/9 being the anniversary of the martyrdom of King Charles the First of blessed memory, and published at the request of some friends / by Edward Pelling ...</title>
            <author>Pelling, Edward, d. 1718.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 46KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B27952</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12538430</idno>
  <idno type="VID">199754</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2248583036</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing P1091</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">12538430</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B27952)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 199754)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 946:21)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached on the thirtieth of January, 1678/9 being the anniversary of the martyrdom of King Charles the First of blessed memory, and published at the request of some friends / by Edward Pelling ...</title>
                  <author>Pelling, Edward, d. 1718.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 27 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Jonathan Edwin ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1679.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Charles --  I, --  King of England, 1600-1649.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  History --  Restoration, 1660-1688.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>Maria Cecilia Caride </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>Maria Cecilia Caride</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:199754:1"/>
            <p>Imprimatur,</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Febr. 1. 1678/9.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Guil. Sill, R. P. D. Henr. Episc. Lond. a Sac. Dom.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:199754:1"/>
            <p> A SERMON PREACHED On the Thirtieth of <hi>January,</hi> 1678/9. BEING THE ANNIVERSARY Of the MARTYRDOM of King CHARLES the First, of Blessed Memory, AND Published at the Request of some Friends.</p>
            <p>BY <hi>EDWARD PELLING,</hi> Rector of S. <hi>Martyns Ludgate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Jonathan Edwin,</hi> at the Three Roses in <hi>Ludgate-Street.</hi> 1679.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:199754:2"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:199754:2"/>
            <head>A SERMON PREACHED On the Thirtieth of <hi>January,</hi> 1678/9.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>Prov. VIII. 15.</bibl>
               <q>By me Kings reign.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>ERE not the Annals of the <hi>Late Times</hi> written in the Memories of the generality of Men; or were not a fresh Generation sufficiently informed touching that Execrable Murder, whereof their Parents were guilty this Day, it would be necessary for me to give you an account of the sad Occasion of our meeting now. But the Clamour of the World about our ears, the Judgments of God that have a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larm'd us even at our doors, that Reproach and Infamy which this Nation lyeth under, those Miseries we have felt, and those we fore-see; but above all the Consciences in our breasts,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:199754:3"/> cannot but storm us into a Confession, that <hi>this day</hi> the Anointed of the Lord was cut off, the Honour of Christians, the Wonder of Ages, the Mirrour of Kings, the Noblest of Martyrs, and the best of Men. This day that mighty Man fell, by the hands of his own Subjects he fell, by the merciless Ax he fell, before the face of the Sun, and at his own doors he fell; and with him the breath of our Nostrils was taken away, the Joy of the Earth, the Beauty of <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> the Fountain of Law, and the Father of the Church; and all Order, Peace, and Religion followed him, and was buried with him in the same Grave. Be astonished, O ye Heavens, and let the Earth put on her Weeds of mourning; let Rhetorick be silent, and our Thoughts be confounded with horrour; let Christianity hide her Face, and let the Thrones of Princes be co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd with Sack-cloth; let the Voice of Loyalty be still, and let all Faces gather blackness; for this was a thing never seen, never heard of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; the Tongue of Men and Angels is not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to express the black Circumstances of it; that Majesty should be accused for Disloyalty to the People, that Subjects should oppress their Sovereign by such pompous and solemn Artifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Cruelty; that Christians, who are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to <hi>Obey</hi> for Conscience sake, should for Conscience sake <hi>Rebell,</hi> for Conscience sake turn the whole Land into an <hi>Aceldama,</hi> a Field of Blood, and at last be so bold as to cut off, not the <hi>Skirt of his Garment,</hi> but the <hi>very Head</hi> of
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:199754:3"/> the Lords Anointed, and that for Conscience sake too; that they should be so profligate and prodigiously wicked, as to stamp upon all these <hi>unnatural</hi> Proceedings the <hi>sacred</hi> Names of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice and Religion: This is such a <hi>Mystery of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iquity</hi> as no Age can parallel; no History com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth near it, but that which tells us of the Sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and Arraigning, and Condemning and Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting of the Son of God himself.</p>
            <p>But as long as the Fifth of <hi>November</hi> and the Thirtieth of <hi>January</hi> stand in our <hi>Calendar</hi> in Red Letters, we shall never want occasion of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming the World (if it be not inform'd enough already) of the bloody Attempts of the <hi>Romish,</hi> and the <hi>Reformed</hi> Jesuite, the Devil with a Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifix and a Legend, and the Devil with a Bible and <hi>Samuel</hi>'s <hi>Mantle.</hi> I join them together, because like <hi>Sampson</hi>'s Foxes, they set all on Fire, though they are turn'd tail to tail, and their Faces look two contrary ways.</p>
            <p>The Argument which has been used by many men to prove the Papacy to be Antichrist, is this, that the Pope exalteth himself above all that is called God, that is (as some Divines un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand it) above the Kings of the Earth, arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gating to himself a Power over them <hi>in things Spiritual,</hi> and in Temporal matters too, <hi>in ordine ad Spiritualia.</hi> If this be true, I know not how They can rub the mark of the Beast out of Their Foreheads, who pretending to be Reformers, have claimed the same Power over Kings, whom they are pleased to call Tyrants, as the Pope
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:199754:4"/> doth over those whom he is pleased to call He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks. Sure I am, 'tis an Antichristian Principle which was never held till these last days, when men of debauch'd Consciences have counted it a great piece of Religion to be Traytors. And into the bargain, 'tis a Principle so seditious, that I am not afraid to say, 'Twas the Trumpet that sounded a <hi>Battalia</hi> in 1642. And the Ax that cut off the Kings head in 1648.</p>
            <p>I find those who were good Christians, and Loyal Subjects, opposing this Principle through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the late Troubles, (when <hi>Goodwin</hi> and <hi>Bridg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es,</hi> and the rest of those Rebels defended it in Print,) particularly, the Judicious and Excellent Dr. <hi>Hammond</hi> did learnedly confute it in that Treatise of his<hi>—Of Resisting the Lawful Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strate,</hi> which was written in the Heat of the War; And afterwards in his Address to the Lord <hi>Fairfax</hi> and his Council of War, when they had the King in their Clutches. The So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber World saw, that nothing could promote, or justifie a Rebellion, nor erect first a Tribunal for the King's Arraigment, and then a Scaffold for his Execution, but this <hi>Bloody</hi> and <hi>desperate</hi> Doctrine, that <hi>The Magistrate hath his Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity from the People, and that they may re-assume the Authority to themselves, and both Try and Sentence Him, in case of default.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A man might wonder, that since God hath brought a Calm upon this Land by the Happy Restauration of an Exil'd Prince, the same boi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterous <hi>Euroclydon</hi> should rise again upon our
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:199754:4"/> Coasts, to sink this Kingdom <hi>deeper than ever</hi> in a Gulph of miseries; But such is the temper of men who love to swim upon the top, like mire in troubled Waters, that nothing is a great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er <hi>Eye-sore</hi> to them, than <hi>a lasting</hi> Peace. We know, that some pretending to wit and Policy (I wish I may say Christianity too) have decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to this purpose, that <hi>The King is King by Law,</hi> that <hi>Government is not Jure Divino,</hi> but that <hi>the Country-Swain hath as good a Title to his Cot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage as the King hath to his Crown.</hi> And I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fess, if St. <hi>Hobbs,</hi> or St. <hi>Machiavil,</hi> be as Authen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick as St. <hi>Paul,</hi> if once the Scriptures come to be degraded into the same Classis with <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> and the <hi>Voice</hi> of the <hi>People</hi> be made as Authoritative as the <hi>Word of God;</hi> so it is.</p>
            <p>But let them put upon it the best Gloss they can, to make it popular and pleasing to the Rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, it is destructive of all Government, and may be compared to the Locusts, <hi>Rev.</hi> 8. which though <hi>they had comely faces like men, yet were their shapes like unto Horses prepared unto Battel, and had tails like unto Scorpions.</hi> We have found by woful experience, that it hath involv'd this Kingdom in <hi>One</hi> Unnatural War already, and he that is not so quick-sighted as <hi>Lynceus,</hi> may yet easily fore-see, that when ever it shall be radi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated in the Consciences of a Tumultuous Rout (and there be many aking Teeth among us) it will <hi>Ruine</hi> it in another.</p>
            <p>For these Reasons, I hope it will not seem ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>unseasonable;</hi> or <hi>unnecessary,</hi> if to answer
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:199754:5"/> those Obligations, which Religion and Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance both have laid upon me, I discourse at this time touching the Chief Magistrates Authority; and for my Subject, I have made choice of these words of Wisdom, that is, the Son of God, the Wisdom of the Father; <hi>By him Kings Reign;</hi> by his Power and Authority; though they are appointed for the Peoples good, yet are they not the Peoples Creatures; they receive not their Commission from any thing under Heaven; nor is their Power a <hi>Derivative,</hi> from any <hi>Consent, or Suffrage of men,</hi> or <hi>Humane Law;</hi> but from his Appointment who is the Original of all Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and whose Trustees, and Representatives, and immediate Deputies they are. <hi>By me Kings Reign.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I know some have look'd upon this Position, as somewhat too much and too lofty to be grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and would fain have it pass as a piece of Courtship and Flattery brought into Request of late by some Prelates of this Church, by one e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>specially, whose Head was more worth than the Noblest <hi>Dathan</hi>'s that ever followed <hi>Corah</hi> in his Conspiracy. And therefore for the clearing of this matter, I shall endeavour to make it good by Scripture, and Reason, and the Testimonies of the Ancients; which I hope will be enough to satisfie any man but an <hi>Atheist,</hi> but an Unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonable <hi>Machiavillian,</hi> but Haughty and Inso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Innovators, <hi>who are given to Changes, and fear neither God nor the King:</hi> as our <hi>Solomon</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timates, <hi>Prov.</hi> 24. 21.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:199754:5"/> 1. For Scripture. I would fain know what Article of <hi>Faith</hi> is more plainly, and more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presly asserted in the word of God, than this <hi>thing.</hi> Consult the place in <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. 1, 2. <hi>Let every Soul be subject to the higher Powers, for there is no Power but of God, the Powers that be, are ordained of God: whosoever therefore resisteth the Power, resisteth the Ordinance of God.</hi> And at the Fourth <hi>ver.</hi> the Apostle tells us, twice in a Breath, that <hi>the Mgistrate is the Minister of God.</hi> Where he confuteth two very gross mistakes, the one on the Christians part, the other on the Heathens. There were some lately con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted from Judaism to Christianity, who did greatly question whether the <hi>Roman</hi> Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment they lived under then was from God, as that was under the Kings of <hi>Israel.</hi> The Pharisees once put the Case to our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, <hi>Whether it were lawful to give Tribute un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to</hi> Caesar <hi>or not, Mat.</hi> 22. 17. Though they were <hi>forced of Necessity</hi> to submit to the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Yoke, yet they did not think that it was laid upon their necks <hi>by the hand of God.</hi> And therefore that Speech of theirs, <hi>We have no King but</hi> Caesar, <hi>Joh.</hi> 19. was spoken only to curry-favour with Pilate. For their frequent Rebellions, and endeavours to set themselves free from the Heathen's power, were a plain Argument of their perswasion, that their Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>risdiction over them was an Illegal Usurpation; and <hi>Grotius</hi> fetcheth it out of the <hi>Talmud,</hi> that they were wont to say, <hi>We have no King but</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:199754:6"/>
               <hi>God.</hi> Now this opinion, <hi>that the</hi> Romans <hi>were not their Lawful Governours,</hi> continued still in the breasts of some Converts: and for the correcting thereof, St. <hi>Paul</hi> lays down that plain Proposition, <hi>There is no Power but of God.</hi> Again, there was another mistake on the Heathen's part, who, among other Calumnies, did cast this Reproach upon the Christians, that they were disloyal, and seditious; and the pretence for their malicious Accusation was this, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause they cryed up their Liberty, and refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed to Sacrifice to Pagan Deities, and would not swear by the Emperour's Genius, and the like. Therefore, to stop the mouth of Slan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and to tye up the hands of Disobedience, the Apostle lays down this short Proposition, as an undoubted Maxime of Christianity, that <hi>the Powers that be are Ordained of God;</hi> and when St. <hi>Paul</hi> wrote this, the Power was in the hands of <hi>Nero,</hi> who was as great a Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster as ever the World bred, excepting <hi>Crom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well.</hi> Add to this, that of <hi>Daniel, Blessed be the name of God for ever and ever, for Wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and Might are his; and He changeth the times and seasons, He removeth Kings, and setteth up Kings, Dan.</hi> 2. 20. That of the Psalmist, <hi>I have said, ye are Gods,</hi> that is, in His place, and his Delegates, <hi>Ps.</hi> 82. 7. That of our Saviour to <hi>Pilate, Thou couldst have no power, unless it were given thee from Above, Joh.</hi> 19. 11. That, Subjection is required of us <hi>not only for wrath, but also for Conscience sake,</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:199754:6"/> over <hi>which</hi> none but <hi>God alone</hi> hath an <hi>immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate power;</hi> that, he who Rebelleth is not only a Traytor against the <hi>Laws of men,</hi> but a Sinner in grain <hi>against the Laws of God;</hi> and that, as the Wages of sin <hi>in general</hi> is Death, so the reward of <hi>this sin in particular</hi> is Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation; Nothing can add light to these words, that are as clear, and bright as the Sun: and the Result of them plainly is this, That <hi>the Supreme Power is of Divine Right,</hi> because it is set up, not only <hi>by Gods Permission,</hi> but by his <hi>Institution</hi> and <hi>Appointment;</hi> by his <hi>Warrant</hi> and <hi>Ordinance Imperial</hi> do Kings reign: so that he that lifteth up his hand against the <hi>Lords Anointed,</hi> striketh at the Face <hi>of God himself;</hi> as he told <hi>Samuel,</hi> that the <hi>Jews</hi> had rejected Him, (the Lord of Life himself) that He should not Reign over them, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 8. 7.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If now in the second place we argue from Reason: It is impossible to shew by the strength of any Philosophy, that Government can be derived but from God alone. For que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stionless, the World was not created to be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing else but a huge Wilderness; neither were men sent into it only to beat and devour one another like salvage Beasts. God did ever de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign, that we should live <hi>godly, righteous, and sober Lives;</hi> and our <hi>Passions</hi> being so <hi>various</hi> and <hi>turbulent,</hi> and our <hi>Wills</hi> being so <hi>perverse,</hi> we cannot imagine how there should be among us any <hi>Order</hi> without <hi>Rule;</hi> nor any <hi>Rule</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:199754:7"/>
               <hi>Law-Makers;</hi> and therefore a Governour is of <hi>God's Appointment,</hi> who never decreeth the <hi>End,</hi> without decreeing the <hi>Means first.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I know what can be said as to this; <hi>viz.</hi> That every man is born a Free-man by the Charter of Nature; that he comes into the world in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vested naturally with a Title <hi>to it,</hi> and with Liberty <hi>in it,</hi> and so no Man can take <hi>his Inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance</hi> from him, without his own suffrage and consent. Let this be believed, that every one hath power over <hi>his Goods,</hi> whether to keep or alienate them: that he has a power over <hi>his Liberty,</hi> to divest himself of it or no. 'Tis granted, that in <hi>Elective States</hi> men do <hi>volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarily put</hi> their power into the hands of the Chief Magistrate; and 'tis reasonable they should do so, that by these Advantages he may be enabled the better to <hi>protect them.</hi> But when this is done, all is done that is in the power <hi>of Man</hi> to do. There is something else which is the <hi>richest Jewel</hi> in the Governour's Crown, namely <hi>a Power of Life and Death;</hi> he must bear a <hi>Sword</hi> in his hand to execute <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pital</hi> Punishment upon Malefactors in Cases <hi>Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minal;</hi> or else it cannot be that a Kingdom should <hi>stand.</hi> Now, this Power can be given him by <hi>none</hi> but <hi>God himself,</hi> whose Vicegerent and Representative he is. For none hath an <hi>Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Right</hi> to our Lives but <hi>He</hi> that <hi>formed us.</hi> Whatever some <hi>Heathens</hi> have thought, yet it
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:199754:7"/> was never granted by any <hi>Christian,</hi> that a man hath any power to <hi>kill himself.</hi> He may sell his <hi>Estate;</hi> he may give away his <hi>Liberty,</hi> chain himself to an Oar as a Galley-Slave, as a Jew had liberty <hi>by the boring of his Ear through, to become a Servant all his days.</hi> He may open a <hi>Vein,</hi> or amputate a <hi>Member</hi> for the preserva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the <hi>rest;</hi> but <hi>kill himself</hi> he <hi>cannot,</hi> without being <hi>felo de se,</hi> guilty of his own blood: Now, what he is not able to do <hi>himself,</hi> how can he impower <hi>another</hi> to do it for him? How can I <hi>communicate</hi> that to him which I have no <hi>Right to my self?</hi> Since no man is Lord of his <hi>own</hi> life, no man hath liberty to <hi>rob him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self</hi> of it, nor power to warrant a <hi>second Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son</hi> to do it. <hi>Vengeance is mine, I will repay, saith the Lord:</hi> It is <hi>Gods</hi> Sword wherewith the Magistrate strikes; and by Him he is <hi>Ordained</hi> to be an Avenger: By <hi>whomsoever</hi> he is <hi>Chosen,</hi> by <hi>God alone</hi> he <hi>Reigneth;</hi> his Crown and Scep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, his Prerogatives and Royalties he holdeth of <hi>Him,</hi> and of <hi>none besides.</hi> Take the World <hi>distributively</hi> or <hi>collectively,</hi> either Man by Man, or by whole Communities, the King owns <hi>no Superiour</hi> or <hi>Enfranchiser</hi> (much less may he be <hi>invaded</hi> by an <hi>Ʋsurper)</hi> here below.</p>
            <p>All the fear is, that by <hi>this grant</hi> a Monarch's Power will be unlimited: An idle Dream, which some <hi>Demagogues</hi> have held out as a <hi>Flambeau,</hi> to set the World on Fire: For though
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:199754:8"/> he be not under the <hi>fear</hi> of Law, being exempt from all manner of <hi>Penalty,</hi> yet it is confessed by all Divines and Lawyers, that the <hi>directive power of</hi> Laws doth oblige him. Who knoweth not, that <hi>God</hi> hath <hi>bound</hi> him to the respects of <hi>publick Honesty,</hi> though he hath not made him liable to a <hi>publick Rod?</hi> Who knoweth not, that the Laws of <hi>Nature and Religion</hi> do oblige him as he is a Man, and much more as he is Prince? Who knows not, that he is under the <hi>Munici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal Laws</hi> of his Kingdom, such as is the <hi>Petition of Right</hi> here with us? To these he hath <hi>bound himself</hi> by his <hi>Own Consent:</hi> And who knows not, that a <hi>Promise</hi> or an <hi>Oath</hi> obligeth him too? and that sometimes he is <hi>more careful</hi> to keep it than his <hi>very Subjects</hi> are? But yet, if a Prince <hi>will abuse</hi> his Power, and the Law too, he is not subject to any manner of <hi>Compulsion,</hi> being ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countable <hi>only</hi> unto God, who <hi>alone</hi> hath Seal'd his <hi>Commission.</hi> It is a violation of the Laws of God and Nature both, to drag a Supreme Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistrate into a <hi>Court of Judicature;</hi> and I never read but of <hi>two</hi> that were ever <hi>haled</hi> so since the World stood, <hi>the King of</hi> Israel before <hi>Pilate,</hi> and <hi>the King of</hi> England before <hi>Bradshaw,</hi> who was by far the greater Knave of the two, because of his <hi>Malicious</hi> and <hi>Bloody Intention.</hi> For, <hi>Pilate moved</hi> on our Saviours behalf, and <hi>sought</hi> to deliver him; but <hi>This Son of</hi> Belial <hi>contrived</hi> and <hi>intended</hi> our Soveraign's destruction, and <hi>thirsted</hi> for his Blood, and therefore <hi>his</hi> was the <hi>greater Sin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:199754:8"/> 3. But the time spends, and therefore I must touch a little upon the next Argument, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the sense of the Ancients about the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Authority of the Supreme Magistrate. And here I might fill a whole Volume with a Cloud of Witnesses; I, out of the <hi>Heathens</hi> themselves, who had no Candle to guide them but the light of <hi>Nature;</hi> and yet <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Sayeth <hi>Homer, Kings are from God. We look so upon our Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours</hi> (saith <hi>Seneca) as if we saw the immortal Gods themselves;</hi> and divers more have said, that Kings are God's Representatives, <hi>&amp; à Deo secundi,</hi> next of all unto him. 2. Out of the Book of Wisdome, which though it be Apocry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phal, yet is very Ancient, <hi>Power is given you from the Lord, and Sovereignty from the Highest,</hi> Chap. 6. 3. 3. And if you enquire of the <hi>Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Christians; Clement</hi> in his Constitutions will tell you? That the King is, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>The Ordinance of God. Irenaeus</hi> will tell you, that <hi>by whose Command men are born, by his Command Kings are appointed. Tertullian</hi> will assure you, that the <hi>Emperour is from him, from whom the Man was before he was Emperour.</hi> That he hath received his <hi>Power</hi> from his hand, of whom he received his <hi>Soul. Chrysostome</hi> will in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form you, that <hi>'tis the work of Divine Wisdome, that some Rule, and others are in subjection.</hi> And <hi>Epiphanius,</hi> that <hi>the Civil Power is Ordained of God, who alone hath put the Sword of Vengeance into his hand.</hi> And <hi>Augustine</hi> is positive, <hi>that he who enthron'd</hi> Augustus, <hi>enthroned</hi> Nero <hi>too; that he who made</hi> Vespatian <hi>made also</hi> Domitian <hi>an</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:199754:9"/>
               <hi>Emperour; and that he, who set up</hi> Constantine <hi>the Christian, did set up also</hi> Julian <hi>the Apostate.</hi> What shall I speak of after Ages, which have all along spoken to the same effect? And what hath been said to this purpose, must be understood with relation to <hi>Lawful</hi> Magistrates only.</p>
            <p>It sufficeth for the close of this matter, that <hi>it is, and ever hath been,</hi> the <hi>plain</hi> and <hi>honest</hi> Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine <hi>of the Church of England,</hi> and I should have wonder'd, how <hi>any Wise man</hi> should not see it in <hi>the Homily against Rebellion,</hi> but that I do consider, that that <hi>Homily</hi> is a <hi>Looking-glass;</hi> wherein <hi>those,</hi> who have been <hi>Traytors,</hi> cannot but <hi>see</hi> their <hi>own guilt</hi> and <hi>deformity,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore do not care to look at all into it.</p>
            <p>You see by this time <hi>that the King is not by the laws of men,</hi> but <hi>by the Power and Appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God. By him Kings reign.</hi> The infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences now from this are very obvious.</p>
            <p n="1">1. If by <hi>Him Kings reign,</hi> then for <hi>his sake</hi> we are bound to <hi>Obey</hi> them. It is St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Conclusion. <hi>Let every Soul be subject to the higher Powers,</hi> for this Reason, <hi>because there is no Power but of God.</hi> It is an Act of <hi>common Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice</hi> to be subject to him under whose <hi>Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Protection we live:</hi> For why should that man have <hi>any benefit</hi> from <hi>that Ordinance,</hi> which he <hi>will not submit to?</hi> Nay it is a <hi>Prime Act of Religion too</hi> to be obedient to the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistrate, who beareth the stamp and image of <hi>God;</hi> and that, not only <hi>as he is a man,</hi> but chiefly <hi>as he is a Magistrate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I know there are some who <hi>make nothing</hi> of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:199754:9"/> this Command, though the breach of it be attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with no less then <hi>Damnation;</hi> they can <hi>despise Government, and speak evil of Dignities,</hi> and pull them down from <hi>their Thrones,</hi> and take their <hi>Crowns</hi> from their <hi>Heads,</hi> and their <hi>Heads</hi> from their <hi>Shoulders,</hi> and yet think they are very <hi>Godly</hi> men too, and <hi>perhaps the more Godly</hi> for that. But whatever men may pretend, <hi>Godliness</hi> cannot be without <hi>Obedience;</hi> the <hi>fearing of God,</hi> and the <hi>honouring of the King</hi> must go together, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause the King hath <hi>no less</hi> than <hi>God's Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> and such <hi>Religion</hi> as is not cloathed with <hi>Subjection</hi> is plainly nothing else, but the cloak of an <hi>Hypocrite.</hi> According to this <hi>Rule</hi> the best Christians have carried themselves before Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion came to be <hi>Sophisticated.</hi> Witness the whole Company of the old Apologists; <hi>Tertul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian</hi> in particular, who boasted with great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence, that <hi>Nunquam nec Albiniani, nec Nigriani, nec Cassiani inveniri potuerunt Christiani;</hi> that is, <hi>never was a true Christian found to be a Traitor to his Prince</hi> (though some in these <hi>latter</hi> dayes could have wish'd that <hi>that passage</hi> could have never been found in the Writings of <hi>Tertulli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an.)</hi> I cannot but take notice here of an <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly</hi> and <hi>scandalous Evasion,</hi> which has been u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed by some who have come among us, part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly from <hi>Tyber,</hi> and partly from the <hi>Lemain Lake;</hi> and like <hi>Herod</hi> and <hi>Pilate</hi> have consent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed together to do mischief. <hi>Bellarmine</hi> and <hi>Parsons,</hi> and other <hi>Jesuits,</hi> have given <hi>this Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son,</hi> why the <hi>Primitive Christians</hi> rebell'd not, <hi>Quia deerant vires,</hi> Because they wanted strength
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:199754:10"/> And we cannot but lament when we consider that <hi>they,</hi> who have so <hi>bitterly</hi> declaimed against the Papist's, have yet lick'd up <hi>their principles,</hi> and prosecuted <hi>their design.</hi> But 'tis well known that <hi>Buchanan</hi> and <hi>Knox long ago,</hi> and <hi>Goodwin</hi> and his fry <hi>since;</hi> and (within these eight years) the <hi>Author</hi> of that <hi>Expedient,</hi> which was the fore-runner of the <hi>General Indulgence,</hi> have said the very <hi>same thing.</hi> But, not to speak of the <hi>quite contrary</hi> Testimonies of <hi>Cyprian;</hi> nor of the <hi>Thebanlegion,</hi> consisting of above 6000. in the Reign of <hi>Dioclesian,</hi> who suffer'd them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves to be cut in pieces rather than they would rebel; <hi>Tertullian</hi> himself said, that they <hi>wanted not forces</hi> to revenge themselves, <hi>seeing all places were fill'd with great numbers of Christians; Cities and Islands, Towns and Castles, nay the very Senate, Court and Camp swarming with men of the Christian Profession;</hi> and 'tis well known that <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian</hi> the Apostate's Army consisted of <hi>Christians</hi> for the most part, who though they had the Sword in their <hi>hands,</hi> yet could not lift them up, but in <hi>Prayer to God,</hi> that he would divert the Emperour's most <hi>wicked</hi> designs. Religion is so far from <hi>disturbing</hi> the publick peace, that it settles the King's Throne upon the <hi>surest</hi> Basis: And as <hi>Guiccardine</hi> tells us how it pass'd for a Proverb, that <hi>Proprium est Ecclesiae Romanae odisse Caesares,</hi> it is Natural to the <hi>Church of Rome</hi> to <hi>hate</hi> Princes: So the World can bear witness of the Sons of <hi>this Church,</hi> that they did ever <hi>love</hi> and <hi>honour,</hi> and dutifully <hi>obey</hi> them; and an ingenious and good man, who hath of late
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:199754:10"/> excellently written upon our <hi>Liturgy,</hi> observes, that whereas we pray in <hi>our Letany,</hi> that God would <hi>deliver us from all Sedition, privy Conspi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy, and Rebellion,</hi> nothing to <hi>that purpose</hi> can be found in <hi>any</hi> of the <hi>Roman</hi> Missals: It is a Glory belonging to <hi>this Church,</hi> that as all her <hi>doctrines</hi> are <hi>pure,</hi> so all her <hi>practices,</hi> and <hi>prayers</hi> are <hi>loyal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>If by him Kings reign:</hi> Then beware we of those <hi>deceitful workers,</hi> who, like Rats that gnaw in the dark, do <hi>privily</hi> go about to <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermine</hi> Government, by such poisonous Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines as these, <hi>that Kings may be deposed.</hi> For if <hi>all</hi> the powers on the <hi>Earth</hi> cannot <hi>give</hi> a King his Authority and Prerogative, neither can <hi>all</hi> the powers on the <hi>Earth</hi> take them <hi>away.</hi> We know <hi>whose</hi> Creed it is, that the <hi>Pope</hi> is Head of the Church; that Princes hold their Crownes of <hi>him;</hi> that by <hi>his</hi> command their Kingdomes may be taken from them; that a dispensation absolveth men from all manner of <hi>Oaths,</hi> and an Excommunication doth discharge them from their <hi>Allegiance;</hi> that, if Subjects <hi>cannot</hi> depose their King but by <hi>War,</hi> then they may raise an <hi>Army,</hi> and proclaim him a <hi>common E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy,</hi> and at last take away his <hi>life:</hi> nay, that though sentence be not <hi>formally pronounced</hi> against him <hi>Ex Cathedrâ,</hi> yet a Prince his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>guilty</hi> of Heresie doth <hi>ipso facto</hi> deprive him of all his Royalties, and <hi>any private person</hi> whatsoever may lawfuly kill him. Hence it was that <hi>Chilperick</hi> of <hi>France</hi> was dethron'd; that <hi>Francis Dandalus</hi> of <hi>Venice</hi> was bound
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:199754:11"/> with chains, and fed like a dog with scraps and bones; that <hi>Henry</hi> the third was murder'd by <hi>Clement,</hi> and <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth by <hi>Ravaillac.</hi> These are such deep staines in his <hi>Holiness</hi>'s <hi>Sleeve,</hi> that all the waters of <hi>Tiber</hi> will not wash them out. Indeed some of his flatterers have used <hi>this devise</hi> as <hi>Fullers-soap</hi> to take it off, if possible; that these were only the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines of the <hi>Canonists,</hi> and a <hi>few more;</hi> and the practices of some <hi>private men;</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they take it ill that they should charge it upon their <hi>whole Church:</hi> But 'tis observable what we find in the <hi>Controversial Letters,</hi> that when <hi>Blackwell,</hi> the Arch-Priest, advis'd the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish</hi> Recusants to take the Oath of Allegiance, the <hi>Pope</hi> sent over a Breve, and forbad the Oath: and <hi>Bellarmine</hi> reprehended <hi>Blackwell</hi> for an Apostate from the <hi>Catholick Faith.</hi> And in the dayes of King <hi>Charles,</hi> our blessed Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr, <hi>Anno</hi> 47. when there were hopes that <hi>all</hi> parties would <hi>agree,</hi> the Papists subscribing to some Articles which tended to the confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of our Government, the Old man at <hi>Rome check't</hi> them, and made some <hi>do pennance</hi> for it. And since <hi>this Kings</hi> happy Restaur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation, when the <hi>Irish</hi> Remonstrance came out with hopes of gaining a Toleration, by the renouncing of some <hi>pestilent Doctrines, Peter Walsh</hi> the Contriver of it was <hi>Censur'd</hi> for his <hi>disobedience</hi> to the infallible Sea. To these I shall add but one observation more, that when <hi>Henry</hi> the third of <hi>France</hi> was murder'd, the <hi>Jesuites</hi> wrote a Book <hi>de justâ abdicatione</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:199754:11"/>
               <hi>Henrici tertii,</hi> wherein they affirm that <hi>it is lawful for any man to kill a Tyrant;</hi> and <hi>that Book</hi> was <hi>allowed</hi> at <hi>Rome;</hi> my witness for this is Father <hi>Watson</hi> the Seminary Priest (in his Quodlibets;) and yet that very man, who accused the <hi>Jesuites,</hi> was afterwards <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecuted</hi> for Treason <hi>himself.</hi> And now let the <hi>impartial</hi> world judge how it concerneth <hi>all States</hi> to spew those villains out of their land, who do not only like the Egyptian Frogs <hi>croak</hi> in Kings Chambers, but like so many <hi>Leviathan's</hi> are ready to <hi>devour</hi> them.</p>
            <p>But we must not think, that disloyalty and treason do lurk onely under a <hi>Friers Cool:</hi> it had been well for us, if it had not found shelter under the Schismaticks <hi>Cloak.</hi> We look upon the <hi>Jesuites</hi> as the <hi>very worst</hi> of Papists; because no other Sect is such an enemy to <hi>civil Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> as they. And what a sad consideration is it, that they, who have called themselves the <hi>purest Protestants,</hi> should choose <hi>no</hi> principles to espouse and pursue, <hi>but</hi> the <hi>Jesuites?</hi> Let im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partial men consider what seditious practices King <hi>James</hi> charged some Reformers with in the conference at <hi>Hampton</hi> Court; that, in the <hi>Geneva</hi> Translation of the Bible, the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal Note upon the 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 15. 16. taxeth <hi>Asa</hi> for deposing his Mother only, and not killing her: that <hi>Salmasius</hi> hath marked a sort of men in <hi>England</hi> with as black a coal as ever the Art of man could find; that the two great Apostles of the North did teach, that if Princes were Tyrants, their Subjects were free from all
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:199754:12"/> bonds of Allegiance, that it was as lawful to kill them as Wolves and Bears, and that it is <hi>Blasphemy</hi> to say, (though <hi>Paul</hi> and the old Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers said) that we must obey Kings, be they good or bad. Let us consider that a Book for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly written against the Supreme Civil Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistrate (whereof <hi>Ficlerus</hi> a Papist was thought to be the Author) was proved to have been written by a Dissenter; and that, in the very year when King <hi>Charls</hi> was beheaded, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother book was Printed (and as some say, licensed by the Fag-end of the house of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons) bearing this Title, <hi>Several Speeches deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd at a Conference concerning the power of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament to proceed against their King,</hi> which was found to have been the same with the sediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Pamphlet of <hi>Parsons</hi> the Jesuit, of <hi>Succession to the Crown.</hi> I say, whoso shall consider these things rightly (that I may not mention any new instances, since the discovery of the late devillish Plot) must needs see, that many great Pretenders among us have been plain Jesuites, and we may say of them, as was once said of one of their Fraternity, that they preached such a Gospel as was <hi>clad in Armour.</hi> From such Preachers as these, <hi>Good Lord deliver us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. If it be <hi>by God that Kings reign,</hi> then we may well ask the Question, by whom it is that Kings are murder'd? By God's <hi>permission,</hi> no doubt. He may hold his hand, and not interpose his Omnipotence, to rescue an innocent man from violence, but let things go on in vengeance for a peoples sins: So he suffer'd <hi>Abel</hi> to be mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:199754:12"/> and his own Son to be murder'd; and 'tis no wonder that in wrath <hi>to this Nation</hi> he suffer'd our Good King to be murder'd. But all this will not excuse either <hi>Cain,</hi> or the <hi>Jews,</hi> or the <hi>high Court of Injustice,</hi> which outvyed <hi>Both</hi> in their boldness and wickedness. 'Twas by God's permission that all this was done, but yet by the Contrivance and Instigation of him, who worketh in the children of disobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience. <hi>Ephes.</hi> 2. 2. Before <hi>Judas</hi> betrayed <hi>Christ</hi> the Text saith Emphatically, that <hi>the Devil enter'd into him.</hi> Had not the <hi>Devil</hi> been in him, he could not have betrayed his Master: But considering all the circumstances of that horrible Act committed at this time, it was so diabolical, so transcendently and eminently Diabolical, that the Divel never shewed himself to be an Absolute Prince and Ruler until now. Shall I crucifie <hi>your King?</hi> sayes <hi>Pilate.</hi> The Heathen could not but speak it with <hi>indignation and horrour.</hi> What? <hi>Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifie your King?</hi> 'Tis such a <hi>Base</hi> as well as <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous</hi> Act, as every one, who as but the face of a <hi>man,</hi> though he be never so great a <hi>Villain</hi> cannot, methinks, but blush at the very <hi>thoughts</hi> of it. The <hi>Jews</hi> were an inhumane, and blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thirsty people; <hi>They killed the Prophets,</hi> and <hi>stoned them which were sent unto them,</hi> and yet when <hi>Pilate</hi> put it to the Vote, whether he should <hi>crucifie their King,</hi> they seem'd to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test and abhor it; they said we have <hi>no King but Caesar;</hi> intimating, that had they been satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied that Jesus was their King, they would
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:199754:13"/> not by any means have his blood shed, or so much as lift up a finger against him. To con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm this, our Saviour himself upon the Cross pleaded their Ignorance. <hi>Father forgive them for they know not what they do.</hi> It was <hi>ignorantia Facti,</hi> ignorance of the fact, not of the Law. They knew, by the Laws of God and nature, they ought not to murder any, much less <hi>their King;</hi> but they were not convinced that that man was <hi>He.</hi> But those sordid and degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Traitors, who executed their Malice upon <hi>this holy Martyr,</hi> they <hi>knew</hi> him to be their King, they <hi>confess't</hi> he was so at his tryal. They had <hi>Sworn Allegiance</hi> to him, nay they swore it in a <hi>Solemn Covenant of their own,</hi> in which little was good or <hi>tolerable</hi> but that <hi>very clause;</hi> and to let the world see how little they regard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, either <hi>Humanity</hi> or <hi>Religion, Promises</hi> or <hi>Oaths;</hi> to convince us that they feared neither <hi>Man,</hi> nor <hi>God,</hi> nor the <hi>Divel</hi> himself, they <hi>kept</hi> that Covenant where they should have <hi>broken it,</hi> and <hi>forswore</hi> it where they should have kept it.</p>
            <p>I cannot but <hi>wonder</hi> at the <hi>monstrous</hi> Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crisie of those Times, when the <hi>Glory of God</hi> was set in the Frontispiece of every dismal Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gedy. I have read of <hi>Pompey</hi> the Great, that he erected a Theatre for Digladiators to fence and kill one another in, and, as if intended to san<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifie his horrible Design, he built a <hi>Temple</hi> over it, and dedicated it to <hi>Venus:</hi> so did these cursed Miscreants (whose <hi>Religion</hi> was of the same size with their <hi>Loyalty)</hi> act all along under the <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zour</hi> of <hi>Religion</hi> (Their Father <hi>Lucifer is often</hi>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:199754:13"/>
               <hi>transform'd into an Angel of light)</hi> they <hi>perjur'd</hi> themselves <hi>in the name of the Lord,</hi> enter'd into <hi>a wicked</hi> League <hi>in the name of the Lord;</hi> Levyed and carried on a <hi>Rebellion in the name of the Lord;</hi> proclaimed a <hi>Fast</hi> before the Execution day, (as <hi>Jezebel</hi> did when she saught <hi>Naboth's</hi> bloud,) <hi>in the name of the Lord; in the name of the Lord</hi> they cut off the head of <hi>his Vice-gerent;</hi> and did such wonderful works, as the Sun never saw before, since 'twas created. Religion, that tyeth the hearts of men in a bond of love; Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, which is a Preservative of Government and obedience; Religion, which assigneth an <hi>appartment in hell</hi> to every <hi>Rebel,</hi> and, I believe, the <hi>lowest Dungeon</hi> in hell to every <hi>Regicide;</hi> that, it seems, did bring the <hi>good King</hi> to the block, which should have <hi>upheld</hi> him in his throne. Is this the <hi>Glorious King</hi> they <hi>promised</hi> to make us? Is this the <hi>Holy Reformation</hi> which they <hi>cryed</hi> up to the skies? <hi>Holy</hi> did I say? This <hi>One act</hi> will make the memory of it <hi>odious,</hi> and <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testable</hi> to all eternity; however some make a shift to <hi>wipe their mouths</hi> at last, with the Whore in the Proverbs, as if they had done <hi>no wickedness.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And shall the Bloud of <hi>Charles</hi> the first be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten Thus? However it was spilt upon the Earth, yet the cry of it is gone up to Heaven, and hath returned upon our Heads, in <hi>Plagues</hi> and <hi>Wars,</hi> and <hi>many dismal Fires</hi> by Sea and Land: and if we repent not of it seriously and heartily, it is to be feared that God will enter into Judgement <hi>further</hi> with us yet. The guilt
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:199754:14"/> of that Innocent and Sacred Bloud, is not so <hi>easily</hi> washed off, as an <hi>Act of Indemnity</hi> is made.</p>
            <p>Well, it is time to Conclude. Those black and gloomy days are gone, and God grant we may never see them more. What I have said, was not intended to ease me of my Cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, or to provoke mens Passions (unless it be that of sorrow) or onely to rip open an Old Ulcer to <hi>enrage</hi> the Patient: But to lay before you the <hi>Grand Impiety</hi> of the Fact, which indeed this Solemnity doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire of us in some measure, that out of a deep Sense of this Nations guilt, we may be stirred up (All of us) to be Humbled <hi>True<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> and <hi>Sincerely</hi> for so foul a Crime, and from the bottome of the most penitent hearts to beg of God, not to lay <hi>this Sin,</hi> this <hi>grievous</hi> and <hi>horrid</hi> Sin, to our charge. And in this Duty there are two sorts Concerned.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Those <hi>old,</hi> and <hi>Grey-headed</hi> Rebels, who did either <hi>assist,</hi> or <hi>encourage,</hi> or <hi>countenance</hi> the Murder, and have liv'd to see the fearful <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sequences</hi> thereof: I wish they may have liv'd to repent and be asham'd of the <hi>sin</hi> too. But how many are there, who will not own <hi>them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves</hi> to have had an hand in it, but lay it ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther at the <hi>Jesuites</hi> door, or some where else; far enough, to be sure, from their <hi>own</hi> Threshold? One would think, that men who have been so horribly disloyal to the <hi>Father,</hi> if they were <hi>sensible</hi> of it <hi>indeed,</hi> and convinced in their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sciences that they <hi>sinned,</hi> would long ago (as one
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:199754:14"/> fruit of their Repentance) have shewn the most Dubtiful submission and obedience unto the <hi>Son.</hi> But 'tis sad to consider, that instead of a <hi>sincere Amendment,</hi> they are not yet come so far as to <hi>Judas his Remorse.</hi> For he <hi>Repented himself,</hi> saith the Text, and acknowledg'd that 'twas <hi>Innocent Blood,</hi> which had been betray'd, and that <hi>he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self</hi> had betray'd it, and that he had <hi>sinned</hi> in betraying it: <hi>I have sinned,</hi> said he, <hi>in that I have betrayed the innocent blood,</hi> Mat. 27. 4. Here was a very great sorrow, and that which made him refund the thirty pieces of Silver, and at last to go and hang himself too. I do not wish the men, I now speak of, <hi>Judas</hi>'s <hi>end;</hi> but I hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily wish that they were so <hi>sorrowful</hi> as to confess their <hi>guilt;</hi> and so honest, as to make some Resti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of the <hi>Price</hi> of <hi>Blood;</hi> and moreover, that they were such friends to <hi>themselves,</hi> and so just to the whole <hi>Nation,</hi> as to bring forth such fruits of Righteousness, Peace, and Obedience, as are meet for Repentance. For if they would consider it, 'tis an Eternal reproach (besides many other mischiefs) which they have brought upon Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by the Sin of <hi>this day;</hi> and for it's kind, greater, then what the <hi>Romanists themselves</hi> have hitherto occasioned. They have murder'd Kings <hi>privately</hi> with poyson; they have assassinated Princes <hi>openly</hi> with Knives and Ponyards: but they never yet brought a Monarch to the Block by a sem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance of Judicial proceedings, daring the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty of Heaven by their Superlative Villany. The Jesuite has been but a Puny, in compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of <hi>these Regicides;</hi> and yet I wish there were
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:199754:15"/> no Room for the Prophets complaint, <hi>I hearken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and heard, but they spake not aright; no man repented him of his wickedness, saying, what have I done,</hi> Jer. 8. 6.</p>
            <p n="2">2. But even we <hi>also</hi> are concern'd in the <hi>Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> of the Day, who were <hi>not</hi> concern'd as Actors in the <hi>Sin.</hi> There are thousands of us, that either were then <hi>unborn,</hi> or had not <hi>power</hi> so much as to make an <hi>attempt</hi> to rescue Innocence: and there are many more in this Kingdome, who were so far from helping to cut off the Kings head, that they did not help to drive him to his Scaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold, or to hold him by the Hair, but disown'd and declared against those inhumane, unnatural, and barbarous Proceedings. But this notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing, we are all of us concern'd to be through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly humbled for that, which was acted by <hi>other hands.</hi> For that sin hath redounded to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triment of the <hi>whole Nation:</hi> And that Bloud is still clamarous against us in the language of those Soul's under the Altar, <hi>Rev.</hi> 6. 10. How long, O Lord, Holy and True, dost thou not judge and avenge our bloud on them that dwell on the Earth? and though Vengeance hath been com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon us with a <hi>slow pace,</hi> yet if we repent not in time of our evil courses, God will reckon with us at last, and reckon with us severely too, we have already smarted for this sin in a high de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree; and as the Jews were wont to say: that in every of their Visitations there were some drams of the Golden Calf, so we have Reason to believe, that in every of our Visitations there have been some drops of that Sacred
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:199754:15"/> Bloud, and yet the <hi>Anger of God is not turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed away, but his hand is stretched out still,</hi> either to Correct, or to dash us in pieces. God of his Mercy grant us first sincere and Universal Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and then <hi>Peace</hi> and a lasting Prosperity, for Christ Jesus his sake, <hi>whose Bloud speaketh better things, than the Sacrifices of</hi> Abel. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>